Okay today’s דף daf is קח, Kuf-Chet, מנחות Menachos 108. We pick
up in the middle of קח Kuf-Chet where it says ושמואל אמר.
V’Shmuel Amar. It is eight lines down, line starts with word אומר,
Omer, ושמואל אמר. V’Shmuel Amar. And we’re dealing with the question about
why there was six extra שופרות, Shofrot, a total 13 שופרות Shofrot
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash where money was put in, but
six were put in for moneys that were going to the עולה
לקיץ המזבח Olah L’Keyitz HaMizbeach for an עולה Olah that would be
brought on the מזבח Mizbeach when there was not a lot of
business to keep the מזבח Mizbeach busy. So it seems like things
are always happening in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Often that money
was basically redirected from other קרבנות Korbanot that could not be brought,
particularly certain types of חטאות Chataot and אשמות Ashamot and so on,
but other things as well. So the question is why were there
six? And one answer, which is why we’re bringing this in here,
is that it corresponds to a cow and a calf and a
ram and a sheep and so on, and it has to do
with people donating the money, not redirecting money, donating the money for
an עולה Olah and making sure it’s used for exactly the right
animal that they said according to רבי. Rebbi. But other answers were
given as well in terms of both the different types of animals
they might have begun of, the different types of things that they
might have begun of. And then practical reasons that the כהנים, Kohanim,
one for each day, כהנים Kohanim should not be upset, "you took
the money that could have gone for my day," and so on.
So now we’re going to give other answers. ושמואל אמר V’Shmuel Amar
כנגד מותר חטאות ומותר אשם ומותר אשם נזיר ומותר אשם מצורע ומותר
מנחת חוטא ומותר עשירית האיפה של כהן גדול. keneged Motar Chataot u’Motar
Asham u’Motar Asham Nazir u’Motar Asham Metzora u’Motar Minchat Chote u’Motar Asirit
HaEifah shel Kohen Gadol. Okay,
we quoted this or most of this a few דפים Dafim earlier,
or the next variation that we’re going to see also according to
רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. So שמואל Shmuel said it is basically the
different sources of where this money could have come, but as opposed
to an earlier answer, the answer of בר פדא Bar Padda where
it was different sources but different types of animals, it could have
begun with a cow, could have begun with a goat, here it’s
different categories of קרבנות, Korbanot, which makes more sense. So one is
leftover money of a חטאת Chatat where money was designated for a
חטאת Chatat and then only some of it was used. The חטאת
Chatat itself, if it wasn’t used in the end and it was
a private חטאת, Chatat, could not be redirected, it would have to
let die, but here was money designated or sanctified for חטאת Chatat
where not all of it was used. מותר אשם, Motar Asham, leftover
money for an אשם. Asham. Both of these the הלכה Halacha is
that the leftover money goes for an עולה, Olah, communal עולה לקיץ
המזבח. Olah L’Keyitz HaMizbeach. מותר אשם נזיר מותר אשם מצורע. Motar Asham
Nazir u’Motar Asham Metzora. So we’re going to distinguish between different types
of אשמות. Ashamot. The אשם נזיר Asham Nazir is distinct because it
is done
because to the אשם Asham of the מצורע Metzora is coming to
make a מצורע Metzora טהור Tahor and you do very specific things
with that blood, you put it on his ears, you put it
on his thumbs and toes and so on. An אשם נזיר Asham
Nazir is coming to also to well to re-begin נזירות בטהרה, Nezirut
B'taharah, so it is similar in that it is
about a transforming a state but it still is distinct enough from
the אשם Asham of a נזיר Nazir and both of those are
distinct from a classic אשם, Asham, which is more for a sin,
an אשם גזילות, Asham Gezeilot, an אשם Asham like stealing something and
swearing and denying it, or מעילה, Meilah, misusing of הקדש Hekdesh and
so on. So different types of categories of אשמות, Ashamot, now we
have four, חטאת Chatat and three categories of אשמות. Ashamot.
ומותר מנחת חוטא, u’Motar Minchat Chote, and leftover money designated for a
מנחה Mincha of a sinner, that’s like מותר חטאת Motar Chatat except
it’s a מנחה. Mincha. Okay, this would be for example like or
be case of עולה ויורד, Olah Veyored, a very specific set of
sins at the end of פרשת ויקרא Parashat Vayikra that if you
don’t have enough money for the חטאת, Chatat, the תורה Torah allows
you to bring one that is a מנחת חוטא. Minchat Chote. ומותר
עשירית האיפה של
כהן גדול,
u’Motar Asirit HaEifah shel Kohen
Gadol, and the each day the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would bring
the מנחת חביתין, Minchat Chavitin, a tenth of an איפה, Eifah, and
in a פסוק Pasuk in יחזקאל Yecheskel it calls that a חטאת,
Chatat, so the assumption here is it would follow the same rules,
if there was leftover money that would go each day, you know
they would have separate money each day, that would go toward the
עולה לקיץ המזבח Olah L’Keyitz HaMizbeach like the normal rule of a
חטאת. Chatat. Okay, so what do you have? You have one חטאת,
Chatat, three different types of אשמות, Ashamot, that’s four, חטאת Chatat which
is essentially a מנחה, Mincha, and the מנחת חביתין Minchat Chavitin of
a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, six different sources.
רבי אושעיא אומר, Rabbi Oshaya Omer, and רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya
said כנגד מותר חטאת ומותר אשם ומותר אשם נזיר ומותר אשם מצורע,
keneged Motar Chatat u’Motar Asham u’Motar Asham Nazir u’Motar Asham Metzora, he
agrees with the first four.
ומותר קינים ומותר מנחת חוטא, u’Motar Kinnim u’Motar Minchat Chote, and he
agrees with the מנחת חוטא, Minchat Chote, although he mentioned it last.
So all of those are the five classic sources of חטאות, Chataot,
one normal חטאת, Chatat, three types of אשמות, Ashamot, two of which
are more about status, one מנחת חוטא Minchat Chote for קרבן עולה
ויורד, Korban Olah Veyored, and he disagrees with the last one of
the מנחת חביתין Minchat Chavitin and instead he puts in... in
the
leftover for קינים *Kinnim* for bird sacrifices that also would be brought
in different contexts for a type of a חטאת chatas *Chatas*—that makes
sense, right? Why not? I mean, you've got that's a classic animal
that's a חטאת chatat *Chatas*. So that's what he mentions. For example,
a יולדת yoledet *Yoledes*, who's coming to purify herself would bring these
bird sacrifices. That's one example. Okay, so ושמואל מאי טעמא mai taama,
לא אמר כרבי אושעיא *v'Shmuel mai ta'ama lo amar k'Rabbi Oshaya*? Why
did שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* not say like רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya *Rabbi
Oshaya*? The case of the bird חטאות chatatot *Chata'os* is the more
obvious example. קינים תנא tana, ליה רישא *Kinnim tana lei reisha* because
when the משנה mishna *Mishnah* says that there were thirteen, it first
gives you tells you what all the seven are—we did not read
that—but one of those seven is for the bird sacrifices, and then
the last six are all for this leftover money that gets used
for the עולת קיץ המזבח olat kaitz hamizbeach. *olas keitz hamizbe'ach*. But
one of those seven was explicitly for קינים *Kinnim*, so you don't
need one of the last six to be it. And there's an
obvious answer to this. ורבי אושעיא תני ולא תני קינים *v'Rabbi Oshaya
tani v'lo tani Kinnim*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya *Rabbi Oshaya*, so the first—well, we'll get to the obvious
answer in a second. First, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya, *Rabbi Oshaya* did not have קינים *Kinnim* mentioned in his
in the משנה mishna. *Mishnah*. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, really?
והתני *v'hatani*? But didn't we teach in a משנה mishna *Mishnah*? והתני
רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya *v'hatani Rabbi Oshaya*? But we know that רבי
אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya *Rabbi Oshaya* taught. ותני קינים *v'tani Kinnim*. So and
he has קינים *Kinnim* in the first seven of the משנה mishna
*Mishnah*. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, no. חד לקינים וחד למותר קינים *Chad
l'Kinnim v'chad l'mosar Kinnim*. Now here's the obvious answer. חד לקינים וחד
למותר קינים *Chad l'Kinnim v'chad l'mosar Kinnim*. Of the first seven, that
was money that was being designated specifically לכתחילה lechatchila, *l'chatchila* for the
purpose. So a woman that needed to bring a bird sacrifice, she'd
come, she doesn't want to wait in line, the whole thing, come,
put her money into the קינים שופר *Kinnim shofar*. The כהנים *Kohanim*
would take the moneys from the קינים שופר *Kinnim shofar*, bring the
appropriate number of bird sacrifices as having in mind that they go
for the owners whomever those owners might be. That's the קינים *Kinnim*
of the first seven. This is leftover money for the קינים *Kinnim*
that gets redirected to an עולה olah. *olah* for קיץ המזבח kaitz
hamizbeach, *keitz hamizbe'ach*. That obviously has to be a different שופר *shofar*
because that's going to a different purpose. So that seems like a
very straightforward answer. I still don't know why שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* did
not say it, you know, clearly those need different שופרות shofarot, *shofaros*.
But okay, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that's where רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya
*Rabbi Oshaya* is coming from, not telling us why שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*
did not like—not to me in my mind explaining sufficiently why שמואל
Shmuel, *Shmuel* did not like it. ורבי אושעיא מאי טעמא לא אמר
כשמואל *v'Rabbi Oshaya mai ta'ama lo amar k'Shmuel*? Why did רבי Rebbi
אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya* not say like שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* of the מנחת
חביתין *minchas chavitin* of the כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol*? So
the answer could be because he's already got six without that, but
maybe there's a principled reason he rejects that. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, סבר לה כמאן דאמר מותר של עשירית האיפה asirit haeifa
של כהן גדול kohen gadol ירקב yerakev, *savar lei k'man d'amar mosar
shel asiris ha'eifah shel Kohen Gadol yirakeiv*. Know that that actually has
to be if there's leftover money for that, on the one hand
it's called a חטאת chatat *chatas*, so it can't actually, if there's
leftover, it can't go towards its own purpose of a חטאת chatas,
*chatas*, that's the general rule. Right, what was used for the חטאת
chatas *chatas* gets used, whatever has to go somewhere else. But he
doesn't feel that it's in the category of a normal חטאת chatas.
*chatas* that the leftover money can go to an עולה olah *olah*,
so you're sort of left with no choice, so you just have
to let the money rot. תניא *Tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא
braita *braitisa*. מותר מנחת נדבה nedava, מותר מנחה mincha ירקב yerakev, *Mosar
minchas nedavah, mosar minchah yirakeiv*.
Leftover money of a free-will מנחה mincha *minchah*, the leftover מנחה mincha
*minchah* shall be let to rot. That doesn't make any sense, that's
almost—that's completely incomprehensible. מאי קאמר *Mai kamar*? What does this mean? אמר
רב חסדה הכי קאמר *Amar Rav Chisda hachi kamar*: here's what it
means. מותר מנחת חוטא minchat chote, נדבה nedava נדבה nedava. *Mosar minchas
chotei nedavah nedavah*. If you have leftover money of a מנחת חוטא
minchat chote. *minchas chotei*, it goes for a נדבה nedava. *nedavah*. Not
like we said before, both שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* and רבי Rebbi אושעיא
*Rabbi Oshaya* agreed that leftover money of a מנחת חוטא minchat chote
*minchas chotei* is—excuse me, it is what we said before. נדבה nedava.
*nedavah* here means the נדבה nedavah, *nedavah* of the עולות olos, קיץ
המזבח kaitz hamizbeach. *olos keitz hamizbe'ach*. Right, that's what נדבה nedavah *nedavah*
means: נדבת ציבור *nidvas tzibbur*, it's a free-will of the ציבור *tzibbur*.
So both of—so that agrees with what they both said before. Leftover
money of a מנחת חוטא Minchas Chotei *minchas chotei* goes for עולות
קיץ המזבח *olos keitz hamizbe'ach*, נדבה nedavah. *nedavah*.
And that's מותר עשירית האיפה של כהן גדול Motar asirit haeifa shel
kohen gadol ירקב *mosar asiris ha'eifah shel Kohen Gadol yirakeiv*, but the
leftover money of another מנחה mincha *minchah* of the מנחת חביתין *minchas
chavitin*, the tenth of the איפה eifa *eifah*, the daily that the
כהן גדול kohen gadol, *Kohen Gadol* brings, ירקב *yirakeiv*, has to be
let to rot. That's a חטאת chatas *chatas*, but because it is
not a standard, you know, for חטא *cheit* and not a standard
חטאת chatas. *chatas*, it's only called a חטאת chatas, *chatas* in יחזקאל
Yechezkel, *Yechezkel*, you both can't use the leftover money for another מנחה
mincha *minchah* for another חטאת chatas. *chatas*, that's the הלכה halacha *halacha*
of a חטאת chatas? *chatas*, and it doesn't have the general rule
that leftover חטאת chatas *chatas* money goes to an עולה olah, *olah*
because it is not a classic חטאת chatas, *chatas*. Okay. רבה אמר
אפילו מותר עשירית האיפה motar asirit haeifa. של כהן גדול kohen gadol.
נמי נדבה *Rabbah amar: afilu mosar asiris ha'eifah shel Kohen Gadol nami
nedavah*. So now we're done with the discussion of what the six
שופרות shofarot. *shofaros* were for and now we're dealing with the focus
about whether you what types of leftover moneys go to a מנחה
mincha *minchah* particularly of a מנחה mincha *minchah*, goes to a this
עולת נדבה *olas nedavah* or you have to let rot or other
things. So רבה אמר אפילו מותר עשירית האיפה mosar asiris ha'eifah של
כהן גדול kohen gadol נמי נדבה *Rabbah amar: afilu mosar asiris ha'eifah
shel Kohen Gadol nami nedavah*. So רבה *Rabbah* gives a third
possibility—excuse me, not a third possibility, רבה *Rabbah* is now going back
to... שמואל Shmuel and saying yes, this ברייתא braita said that the
leftover money of the מנחה mincha, of a כהן גדול kohen gadol?
has to be let rot, but he says, but I go back
and I say like שמואל Shmuel said that the leftover money of
the מנחה of a כהן גדול kohen gadol? is like a normal
leftover חטאת chatas, money and that goes for a נדבה, that goes
for the עולת קיץ המזבח. olat kaitz hamizbeach. אלא, Ella, but if
there is something that has to be let rot, because remember, the
ברייתא braisa, did not say explicitly כהן גדול, kohen gadol, it just
said ירקב, it has to rot, and we read into it the
case of the כהן גדול. kohen gadol? Well, that's all very nice,
that's what, you know, רבי Rebbi אושעיא thinks, that that's the כהן
גדול kohen gadol, that is ירקב, but I'm going to read something
else into it.
אלא מותר לחמי תודה ירקב. Ella motar lachmei toda yerakev. If there's
leftover money from the לחם lachm from the bread of a תודה,
toda, that has to be let to rot because, you know, that
is something that comes only to accompany the תודה toda itself, it
doesn't have any independent status. So, as opposed to other קרבנות korbanot
that had independent status, if there's leftover money you use them for
another קרבן, korban, here any leftover money can't be used for another
קרבן, korban, it was, you know, it doesn't, it can't be transferred
to a קרבן korban that has any status by itself. So that
has to be let to rot. Okay, בפלוגתא, beplugta, and that's actually
this what we've just expressed now about what's the story about what
is the thing that is rots and, you know, how do you
treat the the leftover money of a מנחה of a כהן גדול?
kohen gadol That is a debate.
מותר עשירית האיפה asirit haeifa, של כהן גדול kohen gadol. meaning it's
already an established debate. What do you do with the leftover money
of the עשירית האיפה asirit haeifa, of the כהן גדול? kohen gadol
רבי יוחנן אמר נדבה, Rabbi Yochanan amar nedava, you give it for
the נדבה's קיץ המזבח, which is what רבא Rava said and which
is what שמואל Shmuel said.
רבי אלעזר אמר ירקב, Rabbi Elazar omer yerakev, it has to be
let rot, which is what, which is what רבי Rebbi אושעיא said.
מיתיבי, Mativei, I'll ask you on this. We teach in
שקלים, Shekalim, מותר שקלים חולין ומותר עשירית האיפה ומותר קיני זבים וקיני
זבות וקיני יולדות וחטאות ואשמות מותריהם נדבה. Motar shekalim chulin umotar asirit
haeifa umotar kinei zavim vekinei zavot vekinei yoledot vechatatot veashamot motreihem nedava.
So it says if you have leftover extra money that was given
for the שקלים, shekalim, okay, and or then that goes to חולין,
chulin, that goes, it can even go to non-sanctified purposes, which is
a pretty fascinating point, but that's not our focus. The leftover moneys
for עשירית האיפה, asirit haeifa, the tenth of the איפה eifa of
the כהן גדול, kohen gadol and for all of these types of
bird sacrifices, okay, for זב zav and a זבה zava and a
יולדת and leftover חטאות chatatot, and אשמות, ashamot, that all goes for
נדבה. So that sounds like wow, that was like sort of like
straight שמואל, Shmuel, okay? That was like all the cases he led,
he mentioned for the six שופרות, shofaros with the חטאות, the אשמות,
ashamot, the bird sacrifices and the, you know, all and and the
עשירית האיפה, asirit haeifa they all go for נדבה. Actually, I made
a mistake, it's not שמואל, Shmuel it's actually a hybrid of שמואל
and רבי Rebbi אושעיא, because it mentions all the bird sacrifices, which
is רבי Rebbi אושעיא mentioned, and it mentions the עשירית האיפה, asirit
haeifa, which is what שמואל mentioned. So actually exactly the things that
they were debating what to include in the list, right? שמואל mentioned
the עשירית האיפה asirit haeifa. but not the bird, רבי Rebbi אושעיא
mentioned the bird but not the עשירית האיפה, asirit haeifa both of
those are mentioned in this משנה mishna, here about the leftover moneys
that go to, you know, to the עולת קיץ המזבח. But what
you see here is the thing that was really really debated להלכה,
lehalacha, right? Everybody agreed about the הלכה halacha of the leftover bird
money of the bird sacrifice, that that would go for the קיץ
המזבח. What was debated was the עשירית האיפה. asirit haeifa That is
mentioned right here in this משנה. mishna
So that, so that seems to be a clear proof, you know,
like, what do you call it, you know, like שמואל that the
leftover עשירית האיפה asirit haeifa, goes for נדבה. מאי לאו מותר עשירית
האיפה של כהן גדול? Mai lav motar asirit haeifa shel kohen gadol?
Doesn't it mean the tenth of the איפה of the כהן גדול?
לא מותר מנחת חוטא. Lo motar minchat chote. No, you know, it
is funny because normally you just call something a מנחת חוטא, Minchas
Chotei. normally what you call an עשירית האיפה Asiris Ha'eifah is the
כהן גדול, but since a standard מנחה is an עשירית האיפה, asiris
ha'eifah we're going to say what it means is the מנחת חוטא.
Minchas Chotei So שמואל is going to read
this משנה mishna completely, you know, well no, actually excuse me. So
the,
excuse me, I keep on getting this mixed up, not שמואל, רבי
Rebbi אושעיא is going to read this משנה mishna, completely like his
explanation of the six שופרות. Okay, was his explanation the חטאת chatas
and the various types of אשמות, ashamot, that's four, that's mentioned here
in this משנה, mishna. okay, it says right חטאת chatas and אשמות,
ashamot, and then he had the bird sacrifices, that's what it says
here קיני זבים
וקיני זבות וקיני יולדות, kinei zavim vekinei zavot vekinei yoledot, and he
said, right, the what do you call it, and he said the
the מנחת חוטא and that is what he is calling the מותר
עשירית האיפה. asiris ha'eifah Okay, so anyway very nice, but the simple
sense of this משנה Mishnah? Actually is like שמואל that the עשירית
asiris האיפה of the כהן גדול is, you know, does go for
a נדבה, but רבי יאשיה Rebbi Yoshiyah is going to read it
to refer to מנחת חוטא and then actually have this entire משנה
Mishnah be exactly his list of the six things that the שופרות
went for. Fine. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman,
so we have that debate about what is the story about the
מותר עשירית האיפה of the כהן גדול. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק,
Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מסתברא כמאן דאמר מותר עשירית האיפה של
כהן גדול ירקב. mistavera k'man d'amar mosar asiris ha'eifah shel kohen gadol
yerakev. It makes sense the position of רבי יאשיה, Rebbi Yoshiyah, I'm
sorry, keep getting them mixed up. It makes sense the position of
רבי יאשיה Rebbi Yoshiyah that says that you have to let it
rot. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa לא ישים עליה
שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה כי חטאת היא, Lo yasim aleha shemen
v'lo yiten aleha levonah ki chatas hi, that is the פסוק pasuk
about the עשירית האיפה of a מנחת חוטא. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar
Rebbi Yehuda, so said רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, היא קרויה חטאת, hi
k'ruyah chatas,
that
the מנחת חוטא is the מנחה that is called a חטאת, chatas,
ואין אחרת קרויה חטאת, v'ein acheres k'ruyah chatas, but not another one.
Meaning even though the עשירית האיפה of a כהן גדול is called
a חטאת chatas, in יחזקאל, Yechezkel this פסוק pasuk in the תורה
Torah is telling you that's not really a חטאת. chatas Okay. So
it's enough of a חטאת chatas, because it's called that way in
יחזקאל Yechezkel to say that you can't use the leftover money for
anything else, but it's not really a חטאת. chatas, This is exactly
explaining why it rots, because it's caught in between the two. It's
not really a חטאת, so it doesn't have the הלכה halacha that
the leftover money gets used for an עולה. olah, So you're stuck
and you have to let it rot. Okay. לימד על עשירית האיפה
של כהן גדול שאינה קרויה חטאת, Limed al asiris ha'eifah shel kohen
gadol she'einah k'ruyah chatas,
that that is not called a חטאת. וטעונה לבונה, V'te'unah levonah,
and because it doesn't get a חטאת—it's not called a real חטאת
despite what it says in
יחזקאל—what's Yechezkel the הלכה halacha of a חטאת? It says you don't
put on it frankincense, לא ישים
עליה לבונה. lo yasim aleha levonah. So—excuse me—the הלכה halacha of a
real חטאת is that you don't put on it לבונה, levonah, לא
ישים עליה לבונה, lo yasim aleha levonah,
but because the עשירית of the כהן גדול is not a real
חטאת, you do get לבונה. levonah. ומדאינה קרויה חטאת מותרה ירקב, U'mide'einah
k'ruyah chatas mosarah yerakev,
and here's our key: that because it's not a real חטאת, you
have to let the remnant rot. It's enough of a חטאת based
on the פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל Yechezkel that you can't use the
money for another מנחה or for anything else, but it's not a
real חטאת and therefore you have to let it rot. So this
explains exactly what the debate is. The one that says that it
goes for a נדבה says, look, יחזקאל calls it a חטאת, so
any leftover funds go for a נדבה. And the one that says
not says, okay, but it's not really a חטאת, and based on
this פסוק חטאתי, pasuk chatasi, only a חטאת is a חטאת, this
isn't a real חטאת, so it gets לבונה levonah and the money
can't get redirected for an עולה olah, and has to let be
let to rot. Okay, now that's that, and now that's the end
of that whole discussion, we're at least circled back to a מנחה
discussion, which is the main topic of course of our מסכת. maseches.
Next משנה, Mishnah where we're still dealing with people that take vows
and what can they bring to satisfy their vows. שור זה עולה
ונסתאב, Shor zeh olah v'nistayev, somebody said, "this ox is an עולה,"
olah not "I take on myself an obligation," where then the question
is what satisfies the obligation, but you're actually sanctifying the ox itself.
So you have no personal obligation. The question is just how does—what
happens to that sanctity? You sanctified the ox itself and then נסתאב,
nistayev, which is the language to mean it got spoiled, which means
it got a blemish. And now you can't bring it. So you
have to redeem it. אם רצה יביא בדמיו שנים, Im ratzah yavi
bedamav shenayim, you can go ahead and use that money to bring
two עולות, two oxen. Okay? It's not about a personal obligation and
did you satisfy it and can you bring smaller ones, can you
divide the money, etc. Here, there's no obligation. It's just sanctified. You
have to transfer the sanctity now, so you transfer it to two
animals and you bring both of those animals as a קרבן. korban.
שני שוורים אלו עולה ונסתאבו, Shenei shevarim elu olah v'nistavu, "these two
oxen are an עולה," olah and they both got blemishes. רצה יביא
בדמיהם אחד, Ratzah yavi bidmeihem echad, so now you can transfer that
all to one big ox and bring one animal. Okay? So it's
all about the sanctity and just transferring it to a legitimate destination,
not about satisfying some original vow. רבי אוסר, Rebbi oser, רבי Rebbi
prohibits. Now, does he prohibit both of the cases or just the
case of going from two to one? Because you can't have a
smaller number if you started with two, you shouldn't get a smaller
number of sacrifices in the end even if it's bigger. Well, let's
see the next case in the משנה. Mishnah. איל זה עולה ונסתאב
אם רצה יביא בדמיו כבש. Ayil zeh olah v'nistayev im ratzah yavi
bedamav keves. "This ram is an עולה," olah, and it got a
blemish, you can bring a sheep even though it's smaller, you know,
maybe it was just more expensive. That's okay. Similarly again, כבש זה
עולה ונסתאב אם רצה יביא בדמיו איל. keves zeh olah v'nistayev im
ratzah yavi bedamav ayil. If this lamb is an עולה olah and
it got a blemish, if you want you can bring a ram
in its place. That's bigger, that's maybe even more obvious. רבי אוסר,
Rebbi oser, Rebbi forbids. So if רבי Rebbi is forbidding minimally this
last case, and the גמרא Gemara is going to say this, he
doesn't even want you to go up in terms of how it's
being used. It seems like רבי Rebbi is against any changes, not
just going from
two
to one, but he really just is against any changes, whether it's
better or worse. And the גמרא Gemara is going to say this.
So let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, top of ק"ח
עמוד ב'. Kuf Chet Amud Bet. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואמרת
רישא שור במנה והביא שניים במנה לא יצא. v'amarta resha shor be-maneh
v'hevi shenayim be-maneh lo yatza. So why does it say here that
you know, you can start from one and bring two? Didn't we
say that somebody who obligates himself to bring an ox with a
מנה maneh can't bring two oxen with a מנה? maneh? You know,
you have to go exactly what you vowed. It's not just about
the money. So גמרא Gemara says, שור זה ונסתאב שאני, shor zeh
u'nistaiv shani, it says the obvious thing without even explaining the logic
behind it. No, when you don't take a personal vow and then
the question is have you satisfied what you've obligated yourself in, you
just sanctified it. Now the question is just fine, the money has
to get repurposed, but it's about, you know, it's but but there's
no designated vow or a requirement that it has to satisfy. It's
just the הלכה that when something has the sanctity of an עולה
it has to be transferred to an עולה, has the sanctity of
a שלמים shelamim transferred to a שלמים, shelamim, but which type of
animal, how many animals, that's not, you know, that there are no
restrictions on. שני שוורים אלו עולה ונסתאבו אם רצה יביא בדמיהם אחד,
shenei shvarim eilu olah venistaavu im ratza yavi bedameihem echad, if you
say two and they got blemishes you can't transfer to one, you
can, excuse me, you can transfer to one, but רבי אוסר Rebbi
oser and רבי Rebbi forbids. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי טעמא,
why is רבי Rebbi forbidding? משום דהוה ליה גדול והביא קטן. mishum
de-havé lei gadol ve-hevei katan. So presumably according to רבי Rebbi that,
you know, it the same way you can't say, you know, obligate
yourself in a big one and bring a small one,
that
so also you can't start with two and bring one, even though
one is bigger and more expensive than each individual, two is always
considered more important. Okay, so now we're saying that the particular understanding
of רבי Rebbi why he forbids is because going from two to
one is going down. And it's sort of like obligating yourself in
a big and bringing a small. ואף על גב דנסתאב לכתחילה לא
שרי רבי, ve'af al gav de-nistaiv lechatchila lo shari Rebbi, and even
though it got a blemish, רבי Rebbi doesn't want you to go,
so he understands the difference between a personal vow and sanctifying, you
don't have a particular criteria you have to satisfy, but רבי Rebbi
doesn't want the thing you transferred to be considered less in any
way. So you shouldn't go from big to small, and you shouldn't
go from two to one, so that's רבי'ס Rebbi's opposition. So the
גמרא says, וליפלוג נמי ברישא, v'liflog nami be-resha, so why doesn't רבי
Rebbi therefore also argue in the first case?
Meaning if for רבי Rebbi it's not just, I mean, the גמרא'ס
Gemara's assuming that it's not just as I just described it about
going down and the next thing is worse, but it's following the
pattern of the personal vow. That the same way if you took
a personal vow, remember, רבי Rebbi, said you're not allowed to go
from big to small or small to big, right? That was the
debate earlier, if you obligate yourself in a small you can go
ahead and bring a bigger, so רבי Rebbi did not want you
switching in either direction on a case of a personal vow. So
here too if this is patterned after that, why then רבי Rebbi.
should not only have a problem with you going from, you know,
big to small, meaning from two to one, he should have a
problem from you even going from, you know, excuse
me,
from big to small meaning from two to one which is, you
know, two is always considered bigger, he should have a problem from
you even going from small to big, from one to two. Okay,
so why doesn't he argue in the first case of the משנה?
Mishnah, First case of the משנה Mishnah. says if one of them
got sanctified you can go ahead and bring two. Why doesn't רבי
Rebbi argue on that as well? So the גמרא says, רבי אכולה
מילתא פליג, Rebbi a'kula milta palig, רבי Rebbi yeah, when he says
רבי Rebbi, forbids, he means he forbids both examples, two to one
and one to two. ונטרו רבנן עד דמסייק מילתיה, venatru rabbanan ad
demaseik miltei, he let the Rabbis, you know, he was quiet, let
the Rabbis finish saying what they had to say, והדר מפלג עלייהו,
vehadar mifalg aleihu, and then he debated. So the משנה Mishnah says,
you know, you can go from one to two or you can
go from two to one, and it says רבי Rebbi. forbids, and
he means he forbids both cases whether you are going from two
to one, which is going from big to small, conceptually big, something
more important to less important, or whether you're going from one to
two, which is going from small to big, רבי forbids it at
least לכתחילה, lechatchila because it's when it's a case of personal vow,
we had the discussion before that you didn't fulfill your obligation according
to רבי, and רבי says even small to big you don't fulfill
your obligation, personal vow. Here because you're sanctifying the animal, he's patterning
it after the personal vow and saying לכתחילה l'chatchila. I want you
to, you know, to go by those rules and therefore I don't...
Big to small, small to big, I don't want you to do
it לכתחילה. L'chatchila תדע, Teida, you should know that this is true
דקתני, d'katani, because it says איל זה עולה ונסתאב רצה יביא בדמיו
כבש. ayil ze olah v'nistav ratza yavi b'damav keves. Look at the
final case of the משנה. Okay, if you start with a ram
you can bring a
sheep, כבש זה לעולה ונסתאב רצה יביא בדמיו איל. keves ze l'olah
v'nistav ratza yavi b'damav ayil. You start with a sheep you can
bring a ram, ורבי אוסר, v'Rebbe oser, Rebbe forbids. So minimally that's
going on the last case of sheep and ram. So here Rebbe
by the second case when he says forbids clearly is forbidding sheep
to ram even small to big. שמע מינה, Shma mina, so you
see that it's a little ambiguous how to read the משנה, but
if you put together the two, it's clear that Rebbe forbids you
to go any type of change. Big to small, small to big,
one to two, two to one, sheep to ram, ram to sheep,
he forbids it all even though it would work because it's not
a personal vow. לכתחילה lechat'chila don't do it based on the structure
of a personal vow. And the same way by a personal vow
Rebbe does not allow small to big, he doesn't allow that here
as well. Okay, איבעיא להו, Ibayi l'hu, they raised the question,
ממינא למינא מאי? mimina l'mina mai? Can you switch non in terms
of big and small or number, but can you switch from one
sort of species to another? If you sanctify a cow, can you
transfer it to a sheep? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear.
שור זה עולה ונסתאב לא יביא בדמיו איל. shor ze olah v'nistav
lo yavi b'damav ayil. If you say this ox
is an עולה and it got a blemish, don't bring an איל,
ayil, a ram. Now you might think it's because it's a different
species, but that's not true, אבל מביא בדמיו שני אילים, aval mavia
b'damav shenei eilim, you can bring two rams. So here we're introducing
even for the rabbis a new concern which is like don't have
the final thing be of lesser cost. You can go from one
to two, two to one, etc., etc. But don't cheat out the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the final thing should be roughly the same
cost. So you see that you can switch the species as long
as from ox to ram as long as you don't really cheat
out in terms of the cost. ורבי אוסר, v'Rebbe oser, and Rebbe
forbids לפי שאין בילה, lefi she'ein bila, because you can't mix. Now
what does "you can't mix" mean? So you can't mix means that
when you bring two rams, you're bringing two מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim
with them. So according to this it sounds like Rebbe doesn't fundamentally
have a problem with you transferring big to small, but he's got
some new problem here which is that if you go from one
to two, you're bringing two מנחות menachos and that looks like very
much significantly different. So we'll see about this בילה bila in a
second, but the basic point is it sounds like for Rebbe fundamentally
he doesn't have a problem transferring animals different from what we've seen,
but he's got a problem going from one to two. And רש״י
Rashi explains because if you transfer animals, people will understand it's transferred
קדושה, kedusha, but if they see you bringing new stuff and two
different מנחות, menachos, then that gets very confusing.
Okay, and therefore that specifically is what he forbids. But before we
get to the בילה, bila, let's take a look. שמע מינה, Shma
mina, so you see the Rabbis are okay with you going from
an ox to ram, it's okay for you crossing species. אי הכי,
i hachi, says the גמרא, if that's true, מאי איריא תרי? mai
irya trei? Then why do they demand that you switch it to
two rams? אפילו חד נמי, afilu chad nami, even one? דהא בנסתאב
לרבנן לא שנא ליה בין גדול לקטן, d'ha b'nistav l'rabbanan lo shana
lei bein gadol l'katan, the Rabbis when it gets a blemish and
you sanctify the animal, they don't care whether you're going from big
to small, small to big. So they shouldn't care if you're going
from a cow to a ram.
תרי תנאי ואליבא דרבנן, trei tana'ei v'aliba d'rabbanan, you're right, this ברייתא
braisa is a different approach to the Rabbis than the משנה. This
ברייתא Braita does care if you're going from big to small or
certainly if you're cheating out the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash by getting
something of significantly lesser value. Okay, so this introduced the idea that
you can switch species, but at least according to this תנא, you
cannot really cheat out the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash in terms of
values. Let's just finish out this new idea about Rebbe about בילה.
bila. רבי יוסי לפי שאין בילה, Rabbi Yosi lefi she'ein bila, you
can't because the two מנחות menachos can't be mixed together. So the
גמרא says טעמא דאין בילה, ta'ama d'ein bila, you can't mix the
two מנחות menachos together, you're bringing separate מנחות, menachos, it's obvious somehow
that you're doing something different than you vowed because you vowed one
with one מנחה, now you're bringing two מנחות. menachos. So
the גמרא says הא יש בילה, ha yesh bila, if you could
mix them שרי, shari, it would be okay? Meaning what happened? What
do you mean? Why is this new problem with בילה? bila? Rebbe's
problem was you can't transfer it from the original thing, even big
to small, small to big, you have to treat it like you
would treat a personal vow. והתנן איל זה עולה ונסתאב רצה יביא
בדמיו כבש כבש זה עולה ונסתאב יביא בדמיו איל. v'hatnan ayil ze
olah v'nistav ratza yavi b'damav keves keves ze olah v'nistav yavi b'damav
ayil. The תנא קמא tanna kamma says you can go from ram
to sheep, sheep to ram, ורבי אוסר, v'Rebbe oser, and Rebbe forbids.
And that's only one animal and that's
not different number of מנחות, menachos, meaning what is this brand new
problem for Rebbe? Rebbe's got a more fundamental issue. So the גמרא
says you're right, תרי. trei. תרי תנאי ואליבא דרבי, Trei Tannai v'Aliba
d'Rebbi, it's two תנאים Tannaim according to רבי. Our משנה assumes according
to רבי any change is a problem, and this ברייתא Braita assumes
to him it's only a problem when you go from one to
two.
ובטהורים עגל והביא פר כבש והביא איל יצא. Uv'tehorim, egel veheivi par,
keves veheivi ayil, yatza. The ברייתא ends and says that when you
are dealing with
pure
animals, meaning animals without a blemish, if it's meaning a personal vow,
if you took a vow to bring a calf and you brought
an ox, a sheep and you brought a ram, you fulfilled your
obligation, meaning, going back to the earlier discussion that in case of
a personal vow, if you said small and you brought big, you're
יוצא. yotzei. סתם כרבנן, Stam k'Rabbanan, that's the Rabbis because רבי said
small and big you're not יוצא yotzei by a personal vow. So
to sum up, when it gets a blemish, you're allowed to transfer,
maybe according to the Rabbis, cross-species, one to two, big, small, maybe
according to the Rabbis you have to make sure that the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash does not get cheated out. According to רבי, there
are two things: number one, his existing principle that you can't go
when you take a personal vow you can't even go from small
to big, and then number two, when you say this is sanctified
and it gets a blemish, you have to לכתחילה apply the standards
of a personal vow, and therefore you can't go in that even
in that case one to two, two to one, small to big,
you can't do any type of change according to רבי. Okay, we'll
end here.